<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 20:29:28 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>/posts/about-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 20:29:28 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/about-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;/images/cover.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Hello Friend&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 10px; width: 300px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;Picture of me!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hello! My name is Mikael Gustafsson and I am a student at Aalto University with a strong passion for video games! I find the industry wholly fascinating and love to immerse myself in what video games have to offer. As such, I also quite enjoy developing games in my free time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think video games have a unique ability to create compelling narratives and fascinating worlds. My projects explore these ideas through my unique focus on level design, environmental storytelling, and technical artistry. I love to play around with expectations and surprise the player by taking normal game conventions and flipping them on their heads. That feeling of surprise and profound discovery is something that only video games as a medium is able to offer and it is definitely something I want to keep working on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>
  &lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;/images/cover.jpeg&#34;  alt=&#34;Hello Friend&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 10px; width: 300px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;Picture of me!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hello! My name is Mikael Gustafsson and I am a student at Aalto University with a strong passion for video games! I find the industry wholly fascinating and love to immerse myself in what video games have to offer. As such, I also quite enjoy developing games in my free time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think video games have a unique ability to create compelling narratives and fascinating worlds. My projects explore these ideas through my unique focus on level design, environmental storytelling, and technical artistry. I love to play around with expectations and surprise the player by taking normal game conventions and flipping them on their heads. That feeling of surprise and profound discovery is something that only video games as a medium is able to offer and it is definitely something I want to keep working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at my projects on this page and feel free to contact me through my email address: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:mikael.gustafsson@aalto.fi&#34;&gt;mikael.gustafsson@aalto.fi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One Last Job</title>
      <link>/posts/one-last-job/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 22:20:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/one-last-job/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Github link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Gusse1/olj_game&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Gusse1/olj_game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
itch.io link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/one-last-job&#34;&gt;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/one-last-job&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RpBcNiPLBqI?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In One Last Job, the player takes control of an advanced delivery robot in a near future Finland, in a town where all of the people have mysteriously disappeared. The delivery robot is given one task: Deliver a CD to an old man&amp;rsquo;s cottage at the end of the road.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Github link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Gusse1/olj_game&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Gusse1/olj_game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
itch.io link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/one-last-job&#34;&gt;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/one-last-job&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RpBcNiPLBqI?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In One Last Job, the player takes control of an advanced delivery robot in a near future Finland, in a town where all of the people have mysteriously disappeared. The delivery robot is given one task: Deliver a CD to an old man&amp;rsquo;s cottage at the end of the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gameplay loop consists of simple puzzle solving, exploring different locations, and a zen-like movement mechanic where the player rhythmically times their clicks to glide through the environment dodging the trees and trash left on the roads.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;/images/olj_image_start.jpg&#34;  alt=&#34;Image of the game One Last Job&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 10px; width: 900px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;The player wakes up amidst the trees&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When the player wakes up, the sun is setting and the fog is lit by the orange sun which is drawing long shadows from trees around the heavily forested narrow road. The atmosphere is a bit dreamy with the empty buildings and strong lighting. This is exemplified by the first building the player encounters, the church. With the whole town being empty, the player is left to read into the town&amp;rsquo;s daily life through posters and scattered objects. People have left their phones in the church, a poster about a lost dog is on the tree next to the church and the Sunday prayer is advertised on the church door.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;/images/olj_image_church.jpg&#34;  alt=&#34;Image of the game One Last Job&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 10px; width: 900px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;The church is lit by the sunlight piercing the sole window&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One Last Job was created as my last project for 2024. My original plan of creating three fully finished short games was coming to an end and I wanted to reflect on this creative journey through this game. This game would showcase downtime. The time between action. Especially in games, this is crucial for pacing. Games like Shadow of the Colossus and Half-Life 2 balance this line excellently in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shadow of the Colossus was a strong point of inspiration for this project. I found the reflective power of that world particularly powerful. I credited this to a couple of factors. The vacancy of the world paired with the large towering buildings makes you wonder about what happened in this place, why are the giants there? The traveling between the epic colossus boss fights gives you time to think about all of this. In addition, the powerful music of Kow Otani is stripped away in these moments and what you are left with is the galloping of your horse (Agro), the chirping of birds and the sloshing of nearby waterfalls. With my game, I wanted to explore this downtime in a new environment. What if there isn&amp;rsquo;t any action? Can you create a compelling game with just downtime?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This game was created using Godot with the Terrain3D addon, Blender, Audacity, and some DaVinci Resolve. In terms of development, this was the smoothest process out of all of the three games. The vision was very clear from the beginning of the project and my laser precision with not missing my self-imposed deadlines for this project helped. I would have liked to do more with this game but I guess this would be true for any game project, big or small.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Sepsis</title>
      <link>/posts/house-of-sepsis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 16:20:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/house-of-sepsis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Github link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Gusse1/hos_game&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Gusse1/hos_game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
itch.io link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/house-of-sepsis&#34;&gt;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/house-of-sepsis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rhesvD_n2QU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;House of Sepsis is a survival horror, first-person shooter that focuses on making the player uneasy and using action and puzzle solving to further immerse the player in a strange world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core of the game is resource management using the blood that the player gathers from dead enemies. This blood can be funneled into either health or ammo, giving the player constant interesting strategic opportunities during combat. The game also features slower moments in between the action to break up the pacing. The puzzles involve being observant and finding switches in the environment. Sometimes these switches turn off by themselves so sometimes timing can be crucial.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Github link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Gusse1/hos_game&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Gusse1/hos_game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
itch.io link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/house-of-sepsis&#34;&gt;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/house-of-sepsis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/rhesvD_n2QU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;House of Sepsis is a survival horror, first-person shooter that focuses on making the player uneasy and using action and puzzle solving to further immerse the player in a strange world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core of the game is resource management using the blood that the player gathers from dead enemies. This blood can be funneled into either health or ammo, giving the player constant interesting strategic opportunities during combat. The game also features slower moments in between the action to break up the pacing. The puzzles involve being observant and finding switches in the environment. Sometimes these switches turn off by themselves so sometimes timing can be crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;/images/hos_static_image.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Image of the game House of Sepsis&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 10px; width: 900px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;A giant frozen in the fog&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The atmosphere is important for eliciting this feeling of unease. In the game, this is enforced through a focus on using aggressive, brutalist architecture and strong colored lighting. Among the fog the player can see huge creatures that are frozen in various positions, sometimes guiding the player down the correct path. The thoughts in the main characters head are represented by jittering text boxes dancing around the screen frantically. Additionally, the game includes short video clips to move the story forward and illustrate visuals that would not be possible with the playable sections.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;left&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;/images/hos_text_image.jpg&#34;  alt=&#34;Image of the game House of Sepsis&#34;   style=&#34;border-radius: 10px; width: 900px;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;right&#34; &gt;Text jittering on the screen after a cutscene&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This game was my attempt at evoking a specific feeling from the player, that being anxiety. The game&amp;rsquo;s theming, mechanics, and visuals all feed into this goal. The main inspirations for this game&amp;rsquo;s feel were older PC shooters (&amp;ldquo;boomer shooters&amp;rdquo;). Otherwise, I looked at a lot of art of brutalist architecture and delved into this idea of &amp;ldquo;biopunk&amp;rdquo;, although, during the development of the game, this biopunk idea took a bit of a backseat to the architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This game was created using Godot, Audacity, Blender, and DaVinci Resolve. This was my first time using Godot so a good portion of creating this game, was learning how Godot should be used. To create the levels I ended up using the Qodot extension which allows you to create Quake levels using Trenchbroom and import them into Godot meshes. This was a really good idea since iteration times were super quick for the levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sidenote: During the creation of this game I was listening to a lot of Radiohead and the song &amp;ldquo;Myxomatosis&amp;rdquo; was something that I often used to get into the mood of working on this game :).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meatball Distortion</title>
      <link>/posts/meatball-distortion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 18:17:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/meatball-distortion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Github link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Gusse1/demon_meatball_unity&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Gusse1/demon_meatball_unity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
itch.io link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/meatball-distortion&#34;&gt;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/meatball-distortion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dMsys44qEgo?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meatball Distortion is a physics-based platformer set in the dreams of a chef who really likes meatballs. In the game, the player becomes &amp;ldquo;Agent Meatball,&amp;rdquo; who must cook themselves to perfection and collect all of the dream fragments while reaching the plate at the end of the level. However, the Chef has a dark secret relating to his famed meatball recipe, which the player must uncover.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Github link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Gusse1/demon_meatball_unity&#34;&gt;https://github.com/Gusse1/demon_meatball_unity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
itch.io link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/meatball-distortion&#34;&gt;https://mikaelgustafsson.itch.io/meatball-distortion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    
    &lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;iframe allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; loading=&#34;eager&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dMsys44qEgo?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video&#34;
      &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meatball Distortion is a physics-based platformer set in the dreams of a chef who really likes meatballs. In the game, the player becomes &amp;ldquo;Agent Meatball,&amp;rdquo; who must cook themselves to perfection and collect all of the dream fragments while reaching the plate at the end of the level. However, the Chef has a dark secret relating to his famed meatball recipe, which the player must uncover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the game, the player plays through six levels while gaining more knowledge about the Chef and his dealings with an entity named &amp;ldquo;Sepsis.&amp;rdquo; The player is aided in their quest by their sidekick, Agent Bentil. These dream levels get progressively more deranged and eerie as the player progresses further into the Chef&amp;rsquo;s psyche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea for this game was born out of an inside joke between my friends. We thought it would be funny if there was a game where the player played as a Meatball and tried to avoid some horror creature along the way. I thought this was a great idea and started iterating on this by taking some ideas out of how the genre of &amp;ldquo;Marble platformers&amp;rdquo; plays (eg. Super Monkey Ball, Marble Blast). I thought the Meatball should be heavier to control and as a logical addition, the meatball should be able to be cooked. I also thought that every platformer would be improved by a grappling hook, so I created the &amp;ldquo;spaghetti hook&amp;rdquo; which added some much-needed depth and excitement to the later levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This game was created using Unity, Blender, and Audacity. With this game, I wanted to finish something in a reasonable time frame. Having worked a fair bit with Unity previously, and having experimented with Blender the previous summer, I was determined to finish the game before the holidays. That did not end up happening but I was able to finish the game in early 2024 while simultaneously working full time which I am quite proud of. The game also has a fair amount of content, probably the most out of the games I created in 2024 with its collectibles and secret levels.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
